Guide to the Mary Klachko papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Mary Klachko Papers,
1852-1995
Klachko, Mary.
22 linear feet (ca. 18,000 items in 42 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079762
Biographical Note
Naval historian. Mary Klachko is the author of a number of histories of naval affairs. Among tnem is the important biography of William Benson, entitled, ADMIRAL WILLIAM SHEPHERD BENSON: FIRST CHIEF OF NAVAL OPERATIONS. This work is the only authoritative and exhaustive account of Bensons̀ life and contribution to American naval success during WW1. As first Chief of Naval Operations, it largely fell upon Benson to prepare the navy for entry into the Firt World War. Klachkos̀ extensive notes go far beyond a mere descriptive account of Bensons̀ life and offer an insightful perspective into British and American naval policy and competition during the first three decades of the 20th century.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents,, memoranda, notes, reports, photographs and printed materials. The Klachko papers are almost entirely made up of her research notes for her biography of Admiral Benson. The material covers all aspects of his life, including his early naval career, his tenure as Chief of Naval Operations, and his Chairing of the U.S. Shipping Board. The catalogued correspondence are mainly replies to Klachkos̀ appeal for information about Benson, the naval and political milieu of earely 20th century, and help to publish, review and edit her growing manuscript. Among the catalogued correspondence are: Norman Angell, Walter Lippmann, Edward House, and Eleanor Roosevelt. The catalogued manuscript is Klachkos̀ bio of Benson bound in 5 parts. It is interesting to note that her final manuscript draft is 1038 pages whereas the published biography merely numbers 268 pages. The rest of the collection is comprised of photos of Benson and other important naval and political figures of the time, and Klachkos̀ extensive research notes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Catalogued Series
Series II: Arranged Series
Subjects
Great Britain.--Royal Navy.; Angell, Norman, Sir, 1874-1967.; Balfour, Arthur James Balfour, Earl of, 1848-1930.; Benson, William Shepherd, 1855-1932.; Bracken, Brendan, 1901-1958.; Burke, Arleigh A., 1901-; Chatfield, Ernie Montacute Chatfield, 1st Baron, 1878-1967.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955.; Eller, Ernest McNeill, 1903-; Geddes, Isabella Gamble,--Lady.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938.; Killearn, Miles Lampson, Baron, 1880-1964.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Oliver, Henry Francis,--Sir.; Pratt, William, V.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Shotwell, James Thomson, 1874-1965.; Willert, Arthur,--Sir.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Wiseman, William, Sir, b. 1885.; Woodward, E. L. (Ernest Llewellyn),--Sir,#d1890-; Biography.; Merchant marine--United States.; Naval history.; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations.; Memorandums.; Photocopies.; Biographies.; Reports.; Photographs.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 4-42. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Access Restrictions
Available for faculty, students, and researchers engaged in scholarly or publication projects.
Acquisition
10/16/1991 M-91-10-16
- Series I: Catalogued Series
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    - Angell, (Sir) Norman (Box 1)
    - Bracken, Brendan Rendall, Viscount (Box 1)
    - Burke, Arleigh Albert (Box 1)
    - Chatfield, Ernie Montacute Chatfield, 1st Baron, 1873-1967 (Box 1)
    - Clinton, Bill (Box 1)
    - Eller, Ernest McNeill (Box 1)
    - Geddes, (Lady) Isabella Gamble (Box 1)
    - Hoover, Herbert Clark (Box 1)
    - House, Edward (Box 1)
    - Killearn, Miles Wedderburn, Baron (Box 1)
    - Lippmann, Walter (Box 1)
    - Oliver, (Sir) Henry Francis (Box 1)
    - Pratt, William V. (Box 1)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Mrs. Franklin D.) (Box 1)
    - Shotwell, James T. (Box 1)
    - Willert, (Sir) Arthur (Box 1)
    - Wiseman, (Sir) William (Box 1)
    - Woodward, (Sir) (Ernest) Llewellyn (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscripts
    - Admiral William Shepherd Benson: First Chief of Naval Operations: Parts 1 and 11 (Box 1)
    - Admiral William Shepherd Benson: First Chief of Naval Operations: Parts lll and lV (Box 2)
    - Admiral William Shepherd Benson: First Chief of Naval Operations (Box 3)
  - Subseries I.3: Photographs
    - Bush, George (Box 3)
- Series II: Arranged Series
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence
    - Akademiya Nauk, USSR. (Box 7)
    - Allard, Dean C. (Box 4)
    - Albion, R.G. (Box 4)
    - American Embassy - London (Box 4)
    - Atkinsin, James (Box 4)
    - Balfour Papers (Box 4)
    - Baruch, Bernard M. (Box 4)
    - Benson, Admiral F. W. (Box 4)
    - Benson, H. W. (Box 4)
    - Benson, Commodore Howard H. J. Benson, June 10, 1955 - 1973, (5 folders ) (Box 5)
    - Benson Biography - Opinion of Readers (Box 5)
    - Bilbie, W.C. (Box 5)
    - Bradford, James C. (Box 5)
    - Braisted, William R. (Box 5)
    - Bremmer, I.A.D. (Box 6)
    - British Admiralty (Box 6)
    - British Foreign Office (Box 6)
    - British Humor (Box 6)
    - British Museum (Box 6)
    - British Navy Staff (Box 6)
    - Brooks, Rosemary (Box 6)
    - Broome, D.M. (Box 6)
    - Browning Papers (Box 6)
    - Canadian Information (Box 6)
    - Carnegie Papers (Box 6)
    - Cavalcante, Bernard (Box 6)
    - Churchill, Winston (Box 6)
    - Columbia University Library. Special Collections (Box 6)
    - Columbia University Press (Box 6)
    - Costello, Daniel (Box 6)
    - Custer, Ben Scott (Box 6)
    - Daniels, Jonathan (Box 6)
    - Dartmouth House (Box 6)
    - Davidson, John Wells (Box 6)
    - Department of Navy - Naval Historical Center (Box 6)
    - Department of State (Box 6)
    - Donald, David (Box 6)
    - Doyle, Sandy (Box 6)
    - Eldridge, Dan (Box 6)
    - Elibank, Arthur (Lord) (Box 6)
    - Eller, Admiral E. M. (Box 6)
    - Ellis, John Tracy (Box 7)
    - Encyclopedia of World War I (Box 7)
    - Federal Archives and Record Center (Box 7)
    - Fitzhardings, L.F. (Box 7)
    - French Archives (Box 7)
    - Fox, William (Box 7)
    - Galway, E. (Box 7)
    - Gateswood, Richard Duncan (Box 7)
    - Gill, Rowland P. (Box 7)
    - Grayson Papers (Box 7)
    - Hankey Papers/Pollen Papers (Box 7)
    - Harbough, William H. (Box 7)
    - Harvard University (Box 7)
    - Hayes, Barbara (Box 7)
    - Hazard, John N. (Box 7)
    - Heinl, R.D. (Box 7)
    - Heyes, Clair (Box 7)
    - Hone, Thomas (Box 7)
    - Hooper Edwin B. (Box 7)
    - Hoover, Herbert (Box 7)
    - Hughes Papers (Box 7A)
    - Ingersoll, Rogall C. (Box 7A)
    - Jackson, Richard H. (Box 7A)
    - John, Harry (Box 7A)
    - Johnston, A.C. (Box 7A)
    - Kane, John R.H. (Box 7A)
    - Kaspi, Andre (Box 7A)
    - Kemp, P. K. (Box 7A)
    - Kerneck, Sterling (Box 7A)
    - King-Hall, (Sir) Stephen (Box 7A)
    - Klachko, Mary Letter of introduction by various people. (Box 7A)
    - Krafft, Mrs. H. F. (Box 7A)
    - Kraft, Mary B. (Box 7A)
    - Landau, Helmor (Box 7A)
    - Lewis, Michael A. (Box 7A)
    - Library of Congress (Box 7A)
    - Lloyd George Papers (Box 7A)
    - Longworth, Alice R. (Box 7A)
    - MacDonald, J. Kenneth (Box 7A)
    - MacInnes, J. (Box 7A)
    - Marder, A. (Box 7A)
    - Maywood, J.S. (Box 7A)
    - Milne, Taylor (Box 7A)
    - Ministry of Defence (Box 7A)
    - Miscellaneous letters from friends of Mary Klachko (Box 7B)
    - Mogenburg, Harm H. (Box 7B)
    - Morison, Elting E. (Box 7B)
    - Morrison, Jim (Box 7B)
    - Mouton & Co. (Box 7B)
    - Murrow, Edward R. (Box 7B)
    - National Archives (Box 7B)
    - Naval Historical Foundation (Box 7B)
    - Naval Institute Press (Box 7B)
    - Naval War College (Box 7B)
    - Navy League (Box 7B)
    - O'Connor, Cardinal (Box 7B)
    - Opperman, Herbert (Box 7B)
    - Parsons, Edward (Box 7B)
    - Philadelphia Navy Yard (Box 7B)
    - Princeton University (Box 7B)
    - Private collections (Box 7B)
    - Reynolds, P.A. (Box 7B)
    - Roskill, S.W. (Box 7B)
    - Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park (Box 7B)
    - Royal Military College of Canada (Box 7B)
    - Russell & Arnholy (Box 7B)
    - Sawada, Toshio (Box 7B)
    - Seymour, Charles (Box 7B)
    - Sears, J.W. (Box 7B)
    - Shiels, Margaret (Box 7B)
    - Singwell, John E. (Box 7B)
    - Sims Papers (Box 7C)
    - Stade, Dorothy (Box 7C)
    - Stanford University Library (Box 7C)
    - Steed, Wickham (Box 7C)
    - Steed, Mrs. Wickham (Box 7C)
    - Still, William N., Jr. (Box 7C)
    - Stuart, (Sir) Cambell (Box 7C)
    - Takeuchi, Tatsuji (Box 7C)
    - Townshend, Heather (Box 7C)
    - Train, Harold (Box 7C)
    - Trask, Daniel (Box 7C)
    - Trost, Admiral C.A.H. (Box 7C)
    - Wehmueller, Jackie (Box 7C)
    - U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences (Box 7C)
    - United States Naval Institute (Box 7C)
    - Wheeler, Gerald E. (Box 7C)
    - Henry White Papers (Box 7C)
    - Willert, Arthur (Box 7C)
    - Williams, Michael (Box 7C)
  - Subseries II.2: Manuscripts
    - William Shepherd Benson: First Chief of Naval Operations (Box 8)
      [Copy]
  - Subseries II.3: Research Notes
    - American Fighting Naval Ships - Benson: Naval Exam Board Records, (Folders I-3 ) (Box 9)
    - Benson: Naval Exam Board Records - Hearings, 1920, (Folders 4- 5 ) (Box 10)
    - Merchant Marine - Undated American and English Papers (Box 11)
    - Illustrations (photocopies and repro's of photographs, some used in Benson's biography) (Box 12)
    - Research notes, 1852 - 1908 (Box 13)
    - Research notes, 1909 - July 1914 (Box 14)
    - Research notes, August 1914 - June 1914 (Box 15)
    - Research notes, July 1915 - February 1916 (Box 16)
    - Research notes, March 1916 - November 1916 (Box 17)
    - Research notes, December 1916 - March 31, 1917 (Box 18)
    - Research notes, April 1917 - May 31, 1917 (Box 19)
    - Research notes, June 1917 - July 8, 1917 (Box 20)
    - Research notes, July 9, 1917 - August 30, 1917 (Box 21)
    - Research notes, September 1917 - October 19, 1917 (Box 22)
    - Research notes, October 20, 1917 - November 30, 1917 (Box 23)
    - Research notes, December 1917 - February 1918 (Box 24)
    - Research notes, March 1918 - May 1918 (Box 25)
    - Research notes, June 1918 - August 31, 1918 (Box 26)
    - Research notes, September 1918 - October 31, 1918 (Box 27)
    - Research notes, November 1918 - December 10, 1918 (Box 28)
    - Research notes, December 11, 1918 - December, 31, 1918 (Box 29)
    - Research notes, January 1 - 31, 1919 (Box 30)
    - Research notes, February - March 20, 1919 (Box 31)
    - Research notes, March 21 - April 30, 1919 (Box 32)
    - Research notes, May - July 10, 1919 (Box 33)
    - Research notes, July 11 - October 1919 (Box 34)
    - Research notes, November 1919 - February 1920 (Box 35)
    - Research notes, March - July 1920 (Box 36)
    - Research notes, August 1920 - April 1921 (Box 37)
    - Research notes, May - November 1921 (Box 38)
    - Research notes, December 1921 - 1924 (Box 39)
    - Research notes, 1924 - 1967 (Box 40)
  - Subseries II.4: Manuscripts
    - Klachko, Mary Address at American Historical Associaltion and American Military Institute (Box 41)
    - Klachko, Mary Anglo-American Naval Relations Cooperation or Competition? (Box 41)
    - Klachko, Mary Dissertation outline and adstract (Box 41)
  - Subseries II.5: Topical Files
    - Admirals of the New Navy: Makers of American Naval Traditions, 1886-'93 (Box 41)
    - British Humour (Box 41)
    - Burke, Admiral Arleigh Obituaries (Box 41)
    - Columbia University Mementos (Box 41)
    - Biographical Notes re. Mary Klachko (Box 41)
    - Mary Klachko's organizational membership (Box 41)
    - Photocopies of articles which mention Mary Klachko (Box 41)
    - Photographs and Clippings (Box 42)